[music]
>> Eltham Palace in Southeast London is one
of the best examples of 1930s Art Deco
design in the world.
>> [music]
>> One of my favorite places.
This place was once the site of a
medieval royal palace, but in 1933,
wealthy textile heir Stephen Courtauld
and his wife Virginia bought the
crumbling property.
They created an entirely new building,
an over-the-top ultra-modern party pad
for the pre-war elite.
I really want to find out exactly who
the Courtaulds were and what on earth
inspired them to do this, to take
[music] a nationally important medieval
monument and to brutally bolt onto it a
1930s country house extension in a style
best described as Metroland Palladian.
Is this a charming architectural folly
or is it something less successful? The
Times at the time described it as an
extremely unfortunately cited cigarette
factory.
I know what I think.
>> [music]
>> There's been some sort of building here
at Eltham Palace for almost [music] a
thousand years.
Located in Southeast London, it would
originally have been surrounded by miles
of beautiful countryside until the city
expanded and engulfed it.
I've always loved [music] this building.
I think because every time I come here,
I'm struck by the sense of passing
through Hollywood-like film sets. I've
lived in Southeast London for over 10
years. I've always been rather proud of
the fact that it's here. A building of
such architectural daring-do in a
slightly scruffy suburban context, but
Eltham Palace has a fascinating history.
In fact, Eltham Palace didn't start life
as a royal palace.
It was originally built as a rather
modest moated manor house.
>> [music]
>> But then in the early 14th century, it
caught the eye of Edward II [music] and
so began its association with royalty.
Over the years, Eltham was extended and
transformed into one of the most
important medieval palaces in [music]
England.
But sadly, it fell out of favor in the
16th century and the beautiful building
fell into decay.
The story of this place appealed to the
Courtaulds so much, they used it as
inspiration for some of the exterior
architecture. Up there are finials based
on chess pieces which allude to the
that Eltham Palace had been owned by a
king, by a queen, by a bishop, and after
he became Sir Stephen Courtauld, by a
knight.
And then his Lady Virginia Courtauld
brings history up to date above the door
there. She's been rather solidly carved
as Vesta, the ancient Roman goddess of
hearth, home, and hospitality, waving to
her newly arrived guests to warm
themselves at her eternal fire and make
the most of her abundant fruit basket.
It's a little nod to the purpose of this
house.
What the Courtaulds wanted here was a
party palace. Everything conceived for
comfort and convenience. And as your
glamorous guests arrived, of course the
first comfort they required was a
convenience. Ladies
and then
gents,
allowing the freshly arrived jet set to
reapply or check a tie before making
their grand entrance
into this, the very epitome of Art Deco
luxury. It's extravagant in its
understatement, elegant in its chic.
It's an haute couture interior that's
crowned, quite literally like a
modernist cathedral, by this dome of
concrete and glass.
23 ft wide, each of the hundreds of
circular glass bullets are carefully
placed to trace a series of decreasing
circles, a stunning and surprisingly
efficient way of lighting such a vast
space.
Of course, one of the flaws about living
in a circular room is you can't really
hang pictures. Here, it's been very
expensively resolved because they've
inlaid lots and lots of different
colored timbers to create fine art. But,
what about the subject matter? It seems
a bit random, particularly when you bear
in mind that in this house everything is
significant. Every stick of furniture,
every carpet, every curtain relates back
to the Courtaulds themselves. So, why
have we got a pair of sentinels either
side of the front door? I think it's a
reference to the couple themselves and
their characters. I think that that is
Stephen, a rather reserved, steely-jawed
warrior of the north with his back to
the architectural delights of
Scandinavia. Whereas that, the Roman
soldier, alludes to Virginia's Italian
origins and the glories of Venice and
Florence in minute detail.
So, who were the Courtaulds and how
significant were they to 1930s London
society?
Stephen Courtauld was born in 1883.
Incredibly rich, he inherited a fortune
in shares in his family's textile
business.
Virginia was the daughter of an Italian
father and a Hungarian mother. Stephen
and Virginia married in 1923
and they were an unlikely couple. She
vivacious, impulsive, and chic. He
cautious and reserved.
But together they were hugely popular
and the ultimate party hosts for the
1930s jet-set. There's no doubt that
Eltham Palace was the place to be seen.
By invitation only, this was a favorite
weekend haunt of politicians, [music]
architects, explorers, racing drivers,
film stars, and the royals.
In the dining room, the Courtaulds
wanted a space that put the
in modern and the per in perfect.
Everything had to be bang
up-to-the-minute for the time, even the
technology. This is one of the first
electric fires in the country,
beautifully framed by a black marble
surround. And the lighting, possibly
inspired by the movie industry, bounces
off a silver leaf ceiling, which is so
much more flattering.
Even the chairs were designed to
flatter. Their rose pink color chosen
especially to set off the ladies'
dresses as they dined.
It's these big black lacquer doors that
give the scheme its real originality for
me. You've got the Greek key pattern
that happens elsewhere in the room. So
you've got a nice, gentle, peaceful,
classical framework. But it's this
menagerie of far-flung animals that
really catch the eye. Now, they're not
random. These animals tell travelers'
tales about the Courtaulds' wanderings
and make each door a representation of a
continent they visited and enjoyed.
South America, Africa, India, and I'm
just leaving via Australia.
>> Virginia Courtauld was a well-known
society hostess, and her dining room was
the scene of many a famous dinner party.
>> Life must have been very full for
Virginia. There were weekend parties to
be planned, menus to be approved, and
she did it all here in her boudoir. Now,
I was being rather surprised there's no
desk. There's nowhere to sit. There's
nowhere to write. Until I worked out
that actually she would probably have
reclined here, possibly with a cocktail,
barking at her secretary who was
concealed behind that curtain.
This room speaks volumes about Art
Deco's obsession with streamlining and
space saving. They were inspired by the
age's great love for luxury travel. I
mean, let's face it. This could be the
stateroom in an ocean-going liner. In
fact, I often feel the room itself looks
as if it's going somewhere thanks to
this rather theatrical detail where you
have the cornice reflected in the
mirror.
>> A deliberate design to trick the eye.
>> So, if you want to travel, what you
need, of course, is a map to tell you
where you're going. And here, in
leather, over the fireplace, is a map
with Eltham Palace appropriately right
at the very center.
And concealed in one corner,
a way through to another world.
Stephen's world, Stephen's study. In
fact, Art Deco and Stephen Courtauld
were made for each other. Like him, it
was rational. It was restrained. It was
almost scientifically symmetrical. And
it meant that you could compartmentalize
things. You could keep things in boxes.
In fact, he so feared he so mistrusted
the idea of being disturbed, the
telephone was concealed in there and
only made internal calls so that he
could ring his chauffeur, his secretary,
the Venetian Room, the servery, the
billiard room, or indeed the fire
station.
>> But, if any visitor to the house was
desperate contact the outside world,
they were catered for.
An early payphone was installed in the
lobby.
Judging by the size of the seat, Stephen
didn't want his guest to use it for too
long.
>> And at the end of this corridor beyond
lies one of my favorite rooms. It's one
of the most spectacular in the house and
one of Eltham's biggest surprises.
The lovingly restored Great Hall.
>> [music]
>> Eltham Palace in Southeast London is a
place of contrast.
There's the spectacular 1930s wing,
ultra-modern in every sense from design
to the huge array of mod cons.
And here, you have the very opposite. A
beautifully restored medieval Great
Hall. But, that's what I love about it.
>> The thing about Eltham Palace is because
[clears throat] it's designed to
surprise and delight at every turn.
Every time you think you've got used to
one wonder, there's another wonder to
take its place. Look at this hall.
Absolutely extraordinary. And look at
the hammer roof, 100 ft long, 55 ft
high, and the epitome of medieval
craftsmanship.
To find out more about how this gorgeous
room evolved, I'm meeting with the man
who literally wrote the guidebook on
Eltham.
Michael Turner.
The thing that really strikes me about
Eltham Palace generally is that it's a
kind of an architectural menagerie. You
know, it's a bit like a zoo of different
styles. And this is this is sort of the
prize exhibit, isn't it? What when does
this actually date from and what was it
used for?
>> Well, where we're in now is the Great
Hall, which was Edward the Fourth's
building in the 1470s.
And the idea was that it had to be big
enough to accommodate all the members of
the court.
>> Which of course must have meant that
that Eltham Palace was was first
division palace. It was worth having
somewhere big to meet up in.
>> It was one of the most significant ones
around London. And hence the
construction of the Great Hall anyway,
because Edward the Fourth wanted to, you
know, consolidate it and use it
regularly in addition to Greenwich.
Uh Whitehall and the other palaces.
>> When the court holds first came here,
what did they see? Was it was it a
romantic crumbling ruin?
>> When the court holds arrived, um I think
the site was looking a bit run down. The
uh glazing was um defective in all of
the windows. Most of that gone apart
from the bays.
And it was really being used as a tennis
court. So, wasn't in very good
condition. Lot of bare brickwork. Um
lots of uh the framing exposed on the
screen, for example. And so, they
did an awful lot of work on the roof uh
in terms of a bit more structural work.
They recreated the louvre at the top,
which enabled smoke from the central
fire to waft up uh through the Great
Hall and and out of the louvre. All
those timbers were put back.
So, that was really quite a scholarly uh
effort on their behalf.
>> The thing that I've always loved about
this place is that I've always seen a
rather
almost
almost Hollywood quality to a lot of the
work that was done. I mean, even even
here, even this restoration. Was the
cinema an influence in the way that they
they treated this building?
>> that's a very perceptive question
because of course Stephen Courtauld was
a financial director of Ealing Studios.
So, he was intimately familiar with the
way in which films are made and
particularly the way in which props and
stage sets are created. And there are
lots of interesting things in here which
go well beyond a pure restoration. For
example, these wonderful sort of
Venetian style gondola lanterns that
you've got on the windows, all
electrified, which really do look as if
they've come out of Charles Laughton's
Private Lives of Henry VIII film, which
was released in 1933 at just the time
Stephen and Ginny were thinking about
this place. And I think there's a lot of
that here.
>> So, I mean, what did they use this this
particular space for?
Because obviously, you know, there was
the the height of modern convenience and
and more all the other rooms. Suddenly,
this is you know, this is a complete
change of pace.
>> In terms of everyday use, this was
something like a an oversized sitting
room. There was a wonderful Persian rug
in the middle and there were lots of
easy chairs all the way around. And
don't forget there's underfloor heating
here so that it wasn't cold at all. So,
in spite of the fact that it was a huge
space.
But of course this room I think really
comes into its own when they have a big
party such as a 21st birthday party for
their nephew when
Lou Stone and and his celebrated
orchestra came and led all the dances.
And you could get hundreds, literally
hundreds of guests here sitting down and
eating or everything could be cleared
away and you could have a great dance
party.
>> Although the Courtaulds were great
society [music] hosts, their passions
were not just restricted to dinner and
dancing. They loved the great outdoors
as well. And being the Courtaulds, they
used their house to let everyone know
all about it.
Here to the rear of the house, you can
see this quite clearly.
Everywhere you go, it's obvious that the
Courtaulds relished the opportunity to
personalize the architecture. Out here,
they commissioned the reasonably
well-known sculptor Gilbert Ledward to
create roundels depicting their favorite
pastimes. There's yachting,
there's gardening,
there's what can only be described here
as the classical goddess of holiday
camps. I think those are the only
depiction of shuttlecocks in the history
of sculpture. And around the corner,
there's mountaineering, which Stephen
obviously only did with a full bottle of
champagne in his rucksack.
I wonder what Ledward felt about using
such an impervious and ancient medium of
sculpture to create something quite as
frivolous as this.
It was out here in these vast gardens
landscaped by one of the curators at Kew
that the Courtaulds would have spent
their time with their pets, Caesar the
Great Dane
and Mangeon, the ring-tailed lemur.
Nothing was too good for Mangeon. His
quarters boasted central heating,
delicately painted palm trees, and a
trapdoor down to the flower [music] room
through which he could scuttle and
terrorize the guests.
Even [music] though the Courtaulds loved
having guests and entertaining, they
also cherished their private life.
And it's in the bedrooms more than
anywhere else that you get a real sense
of who these people were.
Like the man himself, Stephen's bedroom
is a quiet, subdued affair. It has the
feeling of sanctuary, of retreat to it.
And even the wallpaper, which is
inspired by his great love of
horticulture, is monochromatic. It's
like a black-and-white home movie.
As was the custom amongst the upper
crust of the day, husband and wife had
separate bedrooms, but here,
this camouflage door has been provided
so the two spaces are joined.
It's really not very hard to guess for
whom this extraordinary bedroom was
created. In fact, the initials VC on the
door over there are completely redundant
because everywhere you look, you see the
rather imperious personality of Virginia
Courtauld. And just look at the way the
bed's been done. You've got lamps,
you've got a niche, you've got these
funny little brackets for offerings.
That is a shrine, a very curvaceous
shrine to femininity. But,
I think the real treat's through here.
This really is 1930s bathing technology
at its most sumptuous. State-of-the-art
meets fine art, allowing Virginia
Courtauld to bob like Venus at her
toilette.
Speaking of which, this Venus's toilet
is hidden behind a rather discreet gold
silk curtain like a private box at the
opera.
>> [music]
>> The Courtaulds were part of the mega
rich.
This whole place [music] was designed
for showing off and elaborate parties.
Ahead of their time, they simply had to
have every mod con.
All eight baths at Eltham Palace could
be filled with hot water at the same
time without it running cold.
Radiator coils embedded in the ceilings
of each room spread gas central heating.
The only exposed [music] radiators are
these luxurious heated towel rails in
every bathroom.
>> [music]
>> But, it was electricity that set Eltham
apart [music] from the rest of the
country.
Eltham was one of the first private
[music] homes to be connected to
Britain's new national electricity grid.
And that meant you could have electric
fires in nearly every room.
Underfloor heating in the great hall.
There were clocks in most rooms, all
synchronized through the [music]
electricity grid.
And loudspeakers hidden in the walls
piped music throughout the [music]
ground floor.
And possibly most advanced of all, every
couple of yards or so, there's one of
these, a socket for sucking, into which
you'd plug a vacuum cleaner removing all
the dust to a centrally contained space.
And depositing it here. [music]
Rather unexpectedly, it's actually down
here in the basement that I feel I found
my first real insight into the mind of
Stephen Courtauld, because whilst all
the splendors, the mod cons, the
luxuries were taking shape upstairs,
down here he created a solid concrete
air-raid shelter 4 years before war was
actually declared in 1939.
You have to remember that Stephen had
been very affected by his time in the
First World War, and as relations with
Nazi Germany began to sour, you can see
him desperately wanting to ensure that
here at Eltham Palace, he was creating
at the heart of his home somewhere safe
for him and Ginny, no matter what the
future held.
He was right to [music] be worried. Just
4 years after the house was completed
during the Battle of Britain in
September 1940,
over a hundred German incendiary bombs
landed on Eltham.
Direct hits destroyed part [music] of
the roof of the Great Hall.
>> [music]
>> The Minstrels Gallery still bears scorch
marks from the burning timbers.
The bombing devastated the Courtaulds.
And just 8 years after they bought it,
they moved out.
First to Scotland,
and then on to Africa and the new luxury
life it offered.
Incredibly, after all the effort that
had gone into restoring [music]
and modernizing Eltham Palace,
Stephen and Virginia
never returned.
The palace had served [music] its
purpose. A place for the 1930s jet-set
to show off, to see and be seen.
Today, it survives as a testament to
[music] pre-war elegance and design.
A unique architectural achievement.
There's no doubt about it, Eltham Palace
[music] is a one-off. It's a building of
extraordinary creativity and great
flair. In fact, if I had to use one word
to describe all of that, it would be
glamour. Because, [music]
no matter what the style, whether it's
Art Deco, modern, ocean-going liner,
Mayfair Venetian bankers baroque, or
indeed original medieval, there's more
than a whiff of Hollywood in its heyday
wherever you go. So, is it an
unfortunately cited cigarette factory,
as the Times called it? I don't think
so. I think it's more like an
architectural dressing up box, a
background to some extraordinarily
grown-up fun.
>> [music]
>> Woo!